A Guide to the Fresh Air Fund Records, 1949-1999
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Fresh Air Fund Records, 1949-1999
Library of Virginia
36407
18.7 cubic feet (41 boxes)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Alice and D. Lloyd Trissel, 30 March 1999.
Biographical/Historical Information
The Fresh Air Fund was established in 1877 by the Reverend Willard Parsons, minister of a small rural Presbyterian parish in Sherman, Pennsylvania. Parsons organized members of his congregation to provide country vacations for children from New York City tenements. Starting in 1882, the NEW YORK TRIBUNE began sponsoring the Fresh Air Fund.
The Fund is made up of Fresh Air children and Friendly Town host families. The children are from low-income families, with the majority receiving some form of public assistance. Friendly Town host families are volunteers who live in suburban communities and small towns. The children stay for a two-week period with the host families during the summer. Since 1877, the Fresh Air Fund has sent more than 1.6 million disadvantaged New York City children to visit with volunteer host families in Friendly Towns in the 13 Northeastern seabord states and Canada.
In Virginia, the Harrisonburg Kiwanis Club sponsored the first Fresh Air Fund children in 1896. In the 1930's the program was discontinued and not reinstated until 1954. In 1955 Alice Trissel became the Rockingham County (Va.) chairperson and the fund representative for Virginia and West Virginia in 1968. Trissel remained fund representative until her retirement in 1995. As of 1999, the Fresh Air Fund was still in existence.
Scope and Content Information
The Fresh Air Fund records are housed in 39 archival boxes and arranged alphabetically by folder title, with ephemera, index cards, and oversized materials arranged to the rear. The collection documents the history of the Fresh Air Fund in Virginia and West Virginia. These materials were gathered by Alice Trissel, Virginia fund representative from 1968 to 1995.
These records include annual reports, clippings, correspondence, histories, memoranda, minutes, pamphlets, photographs, scrapbooks, and other sundry materials. The attendance records comprise the largest section of the collection and contain information on the host families and children from 1954-1993. The records are organized chronologically, then alphabetically by committee. Virginia and West Virginia were divided into eleven area regional committees: Augusta, Broadway/Timberville, Charlottesville, Dayton/Bridgewater, East Rockingham, Harrisonburg/Parkview, Madison, Potomac Valley, Richmond, Shenandoah, and Winchester. These records contain the most comprehensive information on the children and host families, including name, address, occupation, and racial preference. The index cards also contain records of children and host families from 1954-1960 and 1976.
The administration of the Fund's New York office is well documented in the administrative policies, correspondence, manuals, and memoranda. Minutes and agendas for the Friendly Town Conferences can be found in the annual meeting materials. Also of note are the chronological files which contain a variety of materials including correspondence, flyers, and newsletters. These files were maintained in their original order, although materials included in the files may be found elsewhere. Therefore, cross-checking of materials may be necessary to yield all the information on a particular topic.
Also of note are the contest entries and correspondence of the Fresh Air Fund children. The correspondence contains numerous letters from children who stayed with the Trissel family over the years. The collection also contains photographs, posters, publications, and copies of the Fresh Air Fund's newsletter, WHAT'S IN THE AIR. The publications include annual reports, brochures, leaflets, and pamphlets produced by the Fresh Air Fund.
Arrangement
Arranged alphabetically by folder title.
Contents List
- Administrative forms, 1966-1990 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Administrative policies, c. 1970-1993 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Annual meetings: Friendly Town Conferences, 1958-1961 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Annual meetings: Friendly Town Conferences, 1962-1964 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Annual meetings: Friendly Town Conferences, 1965-1970 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Annual meetings: Friendly Town Conferences, 1972-1979 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Annual meetings: Friendly Town Conferences, 1980-1983 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Annual meetings: Friendly Town Conferences, 1984-1986 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Annual meetings: Friendly Town Conferences, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Annual meetings: Friendly Town Conferences, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Annual meetings: Friendly Town Conferences, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Annual meetings: Friendly Town Conferences, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Annual meetings: Friendly Town Conferences, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Annual meetings: Friendly Town Conferences, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Annual meetings: Friendly Town Conferences, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Annual meetings: Friendly Town Conferences, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Attendance records, 1954-1959 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Attendance records, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Attendance records, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Attendance records, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Attendance records, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Attendance records, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Attendance records, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Attendance records, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Attendance records, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Attendance records, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Attendance records, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Attendance records, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Attendance records, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Attendance records, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Attendance records, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Attendance records, 1974 (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Attendance records, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Attendance records, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Attendance records, 1977 (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Attendance records, 1978 (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Attendance records, 1979 (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Attendance records, 1980 (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Attendance records, 1981, Augusta-East Rockingham (Box 6, Folder 3)
- Attendance records, 1981, Harrisonburg-Winchester (Box 6, Folder 4)
- Attendance records, 1982, Augusta-East Rockingham (Box 7, Folder 1)
- Attendance records, 1982, Harrisonburg-Winchester (Box 7, Folder 2)
- Attendance records, 1983, Augusta-East Rockingham (Box 7, Folder 3)
- Attendance records, 1983, Harrisonburg-Winchester (Box 7, Folder 4)
- Attendance records, 1984, Augusta-Harrisonburg (Box 8, Folder 1)
- Attendance records, 1984, Madison-Winchester (Box 8, Folder 2)
- Attendance records, 1985, Augusta-Harrisonburg (Box 8, Folder 3)
- Attendance records, 1985, Madison-Winchester (Box 8, Folder 4)
- Attendance records, 1986, Augusta-Dayton (Box 9, Folder 1)
- Attendance records, 1986, East Rockingham-Harrisonburg (Box 9, Folder 2)
- Attendance records, 1986, Madison-Winchester (Box 9, Folder 3)
- Attendance records, 1987, Augusta-Harrisonburg (Box 10, Folder 1)
- Attendance records, 1987, Madison-Winchester (Box 10, Folder 2)
- Attendance records, 1988, Augusta-Charlottesville (Box 10, Folder 3)
- Attendance records, 1988, Dayton-Madison (Box 11, Folder 1)
- Attendance records, 1988, Potomac Valley-Winchester (Box 11, Folder 2)
- Attendance records, 1989, Augusta-Dayton (Box 11, Folder 3)
- Attendance records, 1989, East Rockingham-Harrisonburg (Box 11, Folder 4)
- Attendance records, 1989, Madison-Winchester (Box 12, Folder 1)
- Attendance records, 1990, Broadway-Harrisonburg (Box 12, Folder 2)
- Attendance records, 1990, Madison-Potomac Valley (Box 12, Folder 3)
- Attendance records, 1990, Shenandoah-Winchester (Box 12, Folder 4)
- Attendance records, 1991, Broadway-Dayton (Box 13, Folder 1)
- Attendance records, 1991, East Rockingham-Madison (Box 13, Folder 2)
- Attendance records, 1991, Potomac Valley-Shenandoah (Box 13, Folder 3)
- Attendance records, 1991, Staunton-Winchester (Box 13, Folder 4)
- Attendance records, 1992 (Box 14, Folder 1)
- Attendance records, 1993 (Box 14, Folder 2)
- Attendance records, nd (Box 14, Folder 3)
- Awards, 1957-1992 (Box 14, Folder 4)
- Calendars, 1989-1997 (Box 14, Folder 5)
- Cartoons, nd (Box 14, Folder 6)
- Chronological files, 1950-1959 (Box 14, Folder 7)
- Chronological files, 1960 (Box 14, Folder 8)
- Chronological files, 1961 (Box 14, Folder 9)
- Chronological files, 1962 (Box 14, Folder 10)
- Chronological files, 1962-1964 (Box 14, Folder 11)
- Chronological files, 1963 (Box 15, Folder 1)
- Chronological files, 1964 (Box 15, Folder 2)
- Chronological files, 1965 (Box 15, Folder 3)
- Chronological files, 1966 (Box 15, Folder 4)
- Chronological files, 1967 (Box 15, Folder 5)
- Chronological files, 1968 (Box 15, Folder 6)
- Chronological files, 1969 (Box 15, Folder 7)
- Chronological files, 1970 (Box 16, Folder 1)
- Chronological files, 1971 (Box 16, Folder 2)
- Chronological files, 1972 (Box 16, Folder 3)
- Chronological files, 1973 (Box 16, Folder 4)
- Chronological files, 1974 (Box 16, Folder 5)
- Chronological files, 1975 (Box 16, Folder 6)
- Chronological files, 1976 (Box 16, Folder 7)
- Chronological files, 1977 (Box 16, Folder 8)
- Chronological files, 1978 (Box 16, Folder 9)
- Chronological files, 1979 (Box 17, Folder 1)
- Chronological files, 1980 (Box 17, Folder 2)
- Chronological files, 1981 (Box 17, Folder 3)
- Chronological files, 1982 (Box 17, Folder 4)
- Chronological files, 1983 (Box 17, Folder 5)
- Chronological files, 1984 (Box 18, Folder 1)
- Chronological files, 1985 (Box 18, Folder 2)
- Chronological files, 1986 (Box 18, Folder 3)
- Clippings, 1949-1959 (Box 18, Folder 4)
- Clippings, 1960-1969 (Box 18, Folder 5)
- Clippings, 1973-1979 (Box 18, Folder 6)
- Clippings, 1980-1985 (Box 18, Folder 7)
- Clippings, 1986-1989 (Box 18, Folder 8)
- Clippings, 1990-1999 (Box 19, Folder 1)
- Clippings, nd (Box 19, Folder 2)
- Community organizations, 1970-1988 (Box 19, Folder 3)
- Contest entries, 1955 (Box 19, Folder 4)
- Contest entries, 1956, Contest #1, Photographs (Box 19, Folder 5)
- Contest entries, 1956, Contest #2, Essays (Box 19, Folder 6)
- Contest entries, 1956, Contest #3, Essays (Box 19, Folder 7)
- Contest entries, 1957 (Box 19, Folder 8)
- Contest entires, 1959 (Box 20, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, Administration, 1954-1984 (Box 20, Folder 2)
- Correspondence, Administration, 1985-1989 (Box 20, Folder 3)
- Correspondence, Administration, 1990-1998 (Box 20, Folder 4)
- Correspondence, Administration, nd (Box 20, Folder 5)
- Correspondence, Administration, Postcards, 1959-1991 (Box 20, Folder 6)
- Correspondence, Fresh Air Fund children, 1959-1984 (Box 21, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, Fresh Air Fund children, 1985-1995 (Box 21, Folder 2)
- Correspondence, Personal, 1960-1983 (Box 21, Folder 3)
- Correspondence, Personal, 1984-1994 (Box 21, Folder 4)
- Correspondence, Personal, Cards, nd (Box 21, Folder 5)
- Correspondence, Personal, Envelopes, 1963-1993 (Box 21, Folder 6)
- Fresh Air Fund events, Flyers 1958-1994 (Box 21, Folder 7)
- Fresh Air Fund events, Miscellaneous, 1961-1995 (Box 21, Folder 8)
- Fresh Air Fund event, Programs, 1968-1994 (Box 21, Folder 9)
- Games, 1989 (Box 22, Folder 1)
- Histories, 1977 (Box 22, Folder 2)
- Manuals, Agency worker, 1978 (Box 22, Folder 3)
- Manuals, Available materials, 1982-1983 (Box 22, Folder 4)
- Manuals, Chairperson's, 1976-1990 (Box 22, Folder 5)
- Manuals, Chairperson's checklist, 1993-1994 (Box 22, Folder 6)
- Manuals, Escort, 1987 (Box 22, Folder 7)
- Manuals, Fund representatives, Section 1 1965-1992 (Box 23, Folder 1)
- Manuals, Fund representatives, Section 2, 1965-1992 (Box 23, Folder 2)
- Manuals, Fund representatives, Interviewer's guide, 1990 (Box 23, Folder 3)
- Manuals, Miscellaneous, Section 1, 1990-1992 (Box 23, Folder 4)
- Manuals, Miscellaneous, Section 2, 1990-1992 (Box 23, Folder 5)
- Manuals, Publicity campaign, 1981-1992 (Box 23, Folder 6)
- Manuals, Publicity workbook, 1984-1989 (Box 24, Folder 1)
- Manuals, Public relations guide, 1993 (Box 24, Folder 2)
- Manuals, Resource book, 1994 (Box 24, Folder 3)
- Manuals, Trainer's guide, 1990 (Box 24, Folder 4)
- Manuals, Training, nd (Box 24, Folder 5)
- Maps, 1992 (Box 24, Folder 6)
- Memoirs, 1993-1994 (Box 24, Folder 7)
- Memoranda, 1955-1990 (Box 24, Folder 8)
- Memoranda, 1991-1993 (Box 24, Folder 9)
- Memoranda, 1994-1995 (Box 24, Folder 10)
- Miscellaneous, 1976-1991 (Box 25, Folder 1)
- Newsletters, Fresh Air Fund, 1953-1965 (Box 25, Folder 2)
- Newsletters, Fresh Air Fund, 1966-1979 (Box 25, Folder 3)
- Newsletters, Fresh Air Fund, 1980-1989 (Box 25, Folder 4)
- Newsletters, Fresh Air Fund, 1990-1997 (Box 25, Folder 5)
- Newsletters, Miscellaneous, 1965-1994 (Box 25, Folder 6)
- Notebooks, 1956-1957 (Box 26, Folder 1)
- Notebooks, 1967-1976 (Box 26, Folder 2)
- Notebooks, 1977 (Box 26, Folder 3)
- Notebooks, 1984 (Box 26, Folder 4)
- Notebooks, 1986 (Box 26, Folder 5)
- Notebooks, 1987 (Box 26, Folder 6)
- Notebooks, 1988 (Box 26, Folder 7)
- Notebooks, 1988-1989 (Box 26, Folder 8)
- Notebooks, 1989 (Box 26, Folder 9)
- Notebooks, 1990 (Box 26, Folder 10)
- Notebooks, 1991 (Box 26, Folder 11)
- Notebooks, 1993 (Box 26, Folder 12)
- Notebooks, 1994 (Box 26, Folder 13)
- Notes, 1959-1994 (Box 27, Folder 1)
- Personnel, Administration, 1983-1991 (Box 27, Folder 2)
- Personnel, Agencies, 1974-1993 (Box 27, Folder 3)
- Personnel, Chairpersons, 1954-1994 (Box 27, Folder 4)
- Personnel, Fund representatives, 1974-1994 (Box 27, Folder 5)
- Personnel, Job descriptions, 1976-1978 (Box 27, Folder 6)
- Photographs, Children, 1956-1985 (Box 27, Folder 7)
- Photographs, Children, 1970 (Box 27, Folder 8)
- Photographs, Host families, Collins, Dorothy, 1950 (Box 28, Folder 1)
- Photographs, Host families, Rolden, Jenny, 1950 (Box 28, Folder 2)
- Photographs, Host families, Wenger, P. Ben, 1950 (Box 28, Folder 3)
- Photographs, Miscellaneous, 1958-1993 (Box 28, Folder 4)
- Photographs, Slides, nd (Box 28, Folder 5)
- Poetry, 1933-1969 (Box 28, Folder 6)
- Promotional materials, 1959-1995 (Box 28, Folder 7)
- Publications, Fresh Air Fund, Annual reports, 1954-1968 (Box 28, Folder 8)
- Publications, Fresh Air Fund, Annual reports, 1970-1983 (Box 28, Folder 9)
- Publications, Fresh Air Fund, Annual reports, 1984-1992 (Box 28, Folder 10)
- Publications, Miscellaneous, 1960-1980 (Box 29, Folder 1)
- Publications, Miscellaneous, 1960-1980 (Box 29, Folder 2)
- Publications, General, 1950-1994 (Box 29, Folder 3)
- Publications, Religious, 1960-1992 (Box 29, Folder 4)
- Public relations, Media lists, 1989-1994 (Box 30, Folder 1)
- Public relations, Miscellaneous, 1960-1994 (Box 30, Folder 2)
- Public relations, Press kit, 1977-1983 (Box 30, Folder 3)
- Public relations, Press releases, 1957-1994 (Box 30, Folder 4)
- Questionnaires, 1988-1990 (Box 30, Folder 5)
- Receipts, 1988-1990 (Box 30, Folder 6)
- Reports, Annual, Virginia chapter, 1964-1983 (Box 30, Folder 7)
- Reports, Annual, Virginia chapter, 1984-1994 (Box 30, Folder 8)
- Reports, Chairperson's checklist, 1968-1987 (Box 30, Folder 9)
- Reports, Chairperson's checklist, 1988-1994 (Box 31, Folder 1)
- Reports, Friendly Town Study, 19779-1980 (Box 31, Folder 2)
- Reports, Miscellaneous, 1959-1980 (Box 31, Folder 3)
- Research paper, 1961 (Box 31, Folder 4)
- Scrapbooks, 1927-1987, Section 1 (Box 31, Folder 5)
- Scrapbooks, 1927-1987, Section 2 (Box 31, Folder 6)
- Scrapbook, 1954-1988 (Box 32, Folder 1)
- Scrapbook, 1957 (Box 32, Folder 2)
- Speeches, 1963-1977 (Box 32, Folder 3)
- Trip records, 1963-1983 (Box 32, Folder 4)
- Trip records, 1984-1986 (Box 32, Folder 5)
- Trip records, 1987 (Box 32, Folder 6)
- Trip records, 1988-1989 (Box 33, Folder 1)
- Trip records, 1990 (Box 33, Folder 2)
- Trip records, 1991 (Box 33, Folder 3)
- Trip records, 1992 (Box 33, Folder 4)
- Trip records, 1993 (Box 33, Folder 5)
- Trip records, 1994 (Box 33, Folder 6)
- Trip records, nd (Box 33, Folder 7)
- Ephemera (Box 34)
- Index cards (Box 35)
- Oversize, Audio/Visual materials (Box 36)
- Oversize, Audio/Visual materials (Box 37)
- Oversize, Scrapbooks (1965-1981: Centennial 1977;1981) (Box 38)
- Oversize, Scrapbook (Years 1949-1970) (Box 39)
- Oversize, Scrapbook (Years 1971-1987) (Box 40)
- Oversize, Posters (Box 41)